Guide to the photograph album "The Gift of the Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of All Burma" - demonstrations during the Iran Oil Crisis (Abadan Crisis), 1951. AD.MC.049
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
"The Gift of the Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of All Burma" - demonstrations during the Iran Oil Crisis (Abadan Crisis), 1951.
Akkasah: Photography Archive (NYU Abu Dhabi)
Mann, Rupert
The Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth
AD.MC.049
40 Photographic Prints Photo album (with hand-painted cover) containing 40 black and white photographs each 15cm x 9.5cm in size, across 21 pages. The album itself is in fair condition, but has suffered from woodworm at some point. The binding has broken, so the pages and covers are not connected. The fabric along the spine has been torn and displays some damage. The external covers are hand painted motifs with a central scene showing three human figures. The inside covers display large Farsi calligraphy. The external covers display scuffing. The back cover has a roughly 3cm by 5cm section missing. The internal pages are in good condition, but have some holes made by woodworm. The photographs are in very good condition. They photos have not been glued to the album but have been attached with plastic corner tabs holding them down. Meaning the photos themselves are undamaged. Photos appear to have been protected from direct light and do not display unusual fading. No significant damage visible. Some photos display discolouration.
Photographs of the 1951 protests in Tehran around the nationalisation of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co (AIOC) during the Abadan Crisis. 12 photos of rural workers. Captions in French. Hand-painted album covers, calligraphic Farsi writing inside covers. Photos depict protests and gatherings in April, May and June of 1951 at a time when the Iranian government was nationalising the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. The newly elected Prime Minister Mosaddeq pushed through the nationalisation with huge local support. The album was sent to a student organisation in Myanmar and the final image is of two young buddhist boys.
Box 049
Content Description
Album of 40 photographs sent as a gift from the "Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of all Burma".
28 photos are of the protests and peace marches in Tehran around the nationalisation of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Co (AIOC) in in April, May and June of 1951 - during the Abadan Crisis. Many of these include women's and youth marches. There are images of the protest against Imperialism in front of the British embassy.
An additional 12 photos are of rural workers and shrines, with a final image of two Buddhist boys. Captions are in French. Hand-painted album covers, calligraphic Farsi writing inside covers.
Conditions Governing Access
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact Akkasah Center for Photography, akkasah@nyu.edu +971 2628 5531
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Rupert Mann (Programs Manager of the Yangon Cultural Heritage Trust), who in-turn purchased it from a street-vendor in Yangon, Myanmar. Prior provenance unknown.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received.
Biographical / Historical
The Iranian Democratic Youth Organisation (the youth branch of the Communist Party of Iran/Tudeh (Sāzmān-e javānān-e Tuda)) was founded in 1943 and is affiliated with the World Federation of Democratic Youth (WFDY). It published Mardom Baraye Javanan (lit. 'People for the Youth') weekly and then Razm (lit. 'Combat') daily newspapers. At the time of the album's creation the Organisation was under the leadership of Nader Sharmini.
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudeh_Youth_Organization https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tudeh_Party_of_Iran https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Federation_of_Democratic_Youth
Conditions Governing Access
Repository permission is required for access. Please contact Akkasah Photography Archive, akkasah@nyu.edu +971 2628 5531
Iran; Politics; Democracy; Crowds; French Writing; Farsi Writing; Abadan, Khuzestan Province, Iran; Communism; Demonstrations/Protests; Myanmar; Tehran, Iran; Mann, Rupert
- Front cover of the album "The Gift of the Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of All Burma" - demonstrations during the Iran Oil Crisis (Abadan Crisis), 1951., AD_MC_049_ref1; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Art; Iran
- Inside cover of the album "The Gift of the Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of All Burma" - demonstrations during the Iran Oil Crisis (Abadan Crisis), 1951., AD_MC_049_ref2; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Farsi Writing; Iran
- Translated captions: Left: University and High School students protest to show their support of the petroleum workers' strike. Right: The youth votes for Peace.", 21 April 1951; AD_MC_049_ref3; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Petroleum industry and trade.; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Men; Facial Hair; Students; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Bicycles/Tricycles; Transportation; Street Lamps; Electricity; Banners; Signs/Signposts; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Photographic Prints; Tehran, Iran; Crowds
- Translated captions: Left: University and high school students' protest. Right: Students and high-schoolers from Tehran protest against the government that killed the students of the Professional School of Abadan.", 21 April 1951; AD_MC_049_ref5; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Farsi Writing; Tehran, Iran; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Petroleum industry and trade.; Politics; Signs/Signposts; Banners; Men; Students; Crowds; Group Portraits; Buildings; Flower Garlands/Bouquets; Streets/Roads
- Translated captions: Left: The police guards the entrance of the Anouchiravan-Dadgar High School to keep young high-schoolers to join their comrades. Right: The youth votes for Peace., 21 April 1951; AD_MC_049_ref7; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Tehran, Iran; Police; Men; Uniforms; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Facial Hair; Women; Demonstrations/Protests; Politics; Democracy; Petroleum industry and trade.; Schools/Education; Students; Hats; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Crowds; Group Portraits; Farsi Writing
- Translated captions: Left and right: A view of the Peace demonstration., 11 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref9; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Crowds; Tehran, Iran; French Writing; Signs/Signposts; Banners; Demonstrations/Protests; Politics; Petroleum industry and trade.; Democracy; Men; Women; Group Portraits; Electricity
- Translated captions: Left and right: Children also take part in the Peace demonstration., 11 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref11; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Tehran, Iran; Girls; Boys; Children; Students; Group Portraits; Women; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Petroleum industry and trade.; Politics; Farsi Writing; Shops; Restaurants/bars; Signs/Signposts; Banners; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Flags; Crowds
- Translated captions: Left: Peace demonstration by the youth. Right: Another view of the same demonstration., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref13; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Tehran, Iran; Signs/Signposts; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Petroleum industry and trade.; Streets/Roads; Crowds; Buildings; Men; Group Portraits; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Banners; Clocks/Watches
- Translated captions: Left: The youth and students' meeting for Peace. Right: Students and high-schoolers of Tehran protest against the government that killed the students of the Professional School of Abadan., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref15; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Men; Students; Crowds; Signs/Signposts; Buildings; Tehran, Iran; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Petroleum industry and trade.; Streets/Roads; Politics; Women; Banners; Bicycles/Tricycles; Transportation; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Clocks/Watches; Electricity; Cars/Trucks
- Translated captions: Left: Young women take part in the meetings and demonstrations., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref17; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Farsi Writing; Tehran, Iran; Banners; Flags; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Petroleum industry and trade.; Women; Students; Men; Crowds; Flower Garlands/Bouquets; Buildings; Streets/Roads; Head Covers/Veils; Signs/Signposts; Group Portraits
- Translated captions: Left: The people of Tehran protest against the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (the 27th of May, 1951) Right:(not in album) The police protect the British embassy on the day of the great protest against imperialism by the people (21 May 1951)., 27 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref19; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Tehran, Iran; Crowds; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Flags; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Petroleum industry and trade.; Electricity; Banners; Women; Streets/Roads; Boys; Girls; Children; Students; Signs/Signposts; Buildings; Eye Glasses/Sunglasses; Men
- Translated captions: Left: The people of Tehran protest against the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. Right: Another view of the meeting., 27 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref21; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Crowds; Banners; Men; Women; French Writing; Farsi Writing; Signs/Signposts; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Petroleum industry and trade.; Politics; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Tehran, Iran
- Translated captions: Left: The people of Tehran protest against the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company. Right: The Tehran women's rally against the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company., 27 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref23; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Banners; Signs/Signposts; Men; Crowds; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Tehran, Iran; Petroleum industry and trade.; Women; Streets/Roads; Head Covers/Veils
- Translated captions: Left: Women's peace demonstration. Right: Participants to the meeting that took place on the 27th of May 1951 vote for the resolution., 27 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref25; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Tehran, Iran; Crowds; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Banners; Signs/Signposts; Streets/Roads; Women; Head Covers/Veils; Men; Group Portraits; Demonstrations/Protests; Politics; Petroleum industry and trade.; Democracy; Buildings; Hats
- Translated captions: Left: Peace demonstration by the people of Tehran, the ranks of women. Right: Another view of the great meeting for Peace., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref27; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Buildings; Crowds; Tehran, Iran; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Women; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Signs/Signposts; Banners; Petroleum industry and trade.; Men; Streets/Roads; Group Portraits; Head Covers/Veils; Girls; Boys; Children; Hats
- Translated captions: Left: The people of Tehran meet to protest against the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company (in front of the National Consultative Assembly (Majlis) with the Shahid Motahhari Mosque is the background). Right: The people of Tabriz protest against the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company., 27 May 1951; AD_MC_049_ref29; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Tehran, Iran; Tabriz, East Azerbaijan Province, Iran; Petroleum industry and trade.; Government; Clocks/Watches; Mosques; Demonstrations/Protests; Democracy; Politics; Signs/Signposts; Banners; Crowds; Buildings; Group Portraits; Streets/Roads; Street Lamps; Electricity; Men; Women; Hats
- Translated captions: Left: Children's demonstration on the 1st of June, 1951, International Children's Day. Right: Demonstration by children., 1 June 1951; AD_MC_049_ref31; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Demonstrations/Protests; Buses; Cars/Trucks; Transportation; Streets/Roads; Buildings; Men; French Writing; Farsi Writing; Flags; Bicycles/Tricycles; Shops; Signs/Signposts; Democracy; Petroleum industry and trade.; Politics; Tehran, Iran; Women; Crowds
- Left: Shiraz, The Tomb of Saadi (Saadieh). Right: Shiraz, The Tomb of Hafez (Hāfezieh)., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref33; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; Farsi Writing; French Writing; Shiraz, Fars Province, Iran; Tombs/Mausoleums; Mountains/Hills; Bicycles/Tricycles; Men; Women; Transportation; Head Covers/Veils
- Translated captions: Left: An iranian farmer. Right: A child (the child of the People experiences poverty from an early age)., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref35; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Individual Portraits; Women; Boys; Children; Hats; Urban agriculture; Head Covers/Veils; Pottery; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints; French Writing; Iran
- Translated captions: Left: The method for threshing in Iran. Right: Plowing of a rice field., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref37; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Agriculture/Farms; Men; Facial Hair; Regional/National Dress; Cattle/Cows; Forest/Woodlands; Animals; French Writing; Machines; Individual Portraits; Iran
- Translated captions: Left: This is how farmers from Isfahan till the soil. Right: This is how children work in factories., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref39; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Factories; Machines; Workers; Boys; Men; Children; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Agriculture/Farms; Iran; French Writing
- Translated captions: Left and right: The people sign the World Peace Council's appeal with enthusiasm., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref41; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Men; Hats; Facial Hair; Head Covers/Veils; Women; Children; Group Portraits; French Writing; Politics; Democracy; Boys; Sheep; Animals; Pens/Inkwells; Iran
- Translated captions: Left: Ferocious exploitation pushes Iranian farmers to beg. Right: An Iranian farmer., 1951; AD_MC_049_ref43; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Men; Boys; Children; Facial Hair; Canes/Walking Sticks; Group Portraits; Agriculture/Farms; Politics; Democracy; Individual Portraits; Iran; French Writing
- Two Buddhist boys., Circa 1951; AD_MC_049_ref44; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Boys; Children; Group Portraits; Regional/National Dress; Religion; Myanmar; Photographic Prints; Gelatin Silver Prints
- Back inside cover of the album "The Gift of the Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of All Burma" - demonstrations during the Iran Oil Crisis (Abadan Crisis), 1951, with handwritten Farsi text: "Young people, unite. March on for permanent peace. Long live the friendship between Burmese and Iranian youths."., AD_MC_049_ref45; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
- Back cover of the album "The Gift of the Centre for Iranian Democratic Youth to Youth Unity of All Burma" - demonstrations during the Iran Oil Crisis (Abadan Crisis), 1951., AD_MC_049_ref46; Unknown; 1 Photographic Prints (Box 049)
  Iran; Art